<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coding | Code for Humanity]]></title>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/blog/categories/coding/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-25T12:12:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vanessahurst.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vanessa Hurst]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ThinkUp Setup: Get better at coding AND social networking]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/thinkup-setup-get-better-at-coding-and-social-networking"/>
    <updated>2013-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/thinkup-setup-get-better-at-coding-and-social-networking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In typical developer style, I just spent several hours hacking on something only to find a totally different way to accomplish the same thing in about ten minutes.</p>


<p>The short version of setting up ThinkUp app was pretty phenomenally easy:</p>


<ol>
<li>Create a free account with a free plan on <a href="http://appfog.com" title="AppFog" target="_blank">AppFog</a></li>
<li>Use Launcher.io's <a href="https://launcher.io/ThinkUp" title="Launcher.io ThinkUp" target="_blank">ThinkUp Jumpstart one-click install</a> (golden!) to deploy to AppFog</li>
<li>Upgrade ThinkUp as prompted in your navigation bar</li>
<li>Update Settings &gt; Account &gt; Enable beta upgrades so you can get the <a href="http://blog.thinkup.com/post/39497204010/thinkup-2-0-getting-better" title="Thinkup 2.0 Beta" target="_blank">snazzy 2.0 beta</a></li>
<li>Upgrade ThinkUp as prompted in your navigation bar (again)</li>
<li>Add social media accounts in the plugins section</li>
<li>Clear your browser's cache</li>
<li>Rock and roll</li>
</ol>


<p>I'm intrigued by ThinkUp for a few reasons:</p>


<ol>
<li>It's <a href="http://github.com/ginatrapani/thinkup" title="Think Up" target="_blank">open source</a>!</li>
<li>It has a <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/thinkupapp" title="ThinkUp community" target="_blank">community that first identifies itself as friendly</a></li>
<li>It has analytics! based on data!</li>
<li>Its core codebase was written by one of my favorite developer-founders, <a href="http://ginatrapani.org/" title="Gina Trapani" target="_blank">Gina Trapani</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dashes.com" title="Anil Dash" target="_blank">Anil Dash</a>,&nbsp;Gina's co-founder,&nbsp;is one of the best twitter users I know (seriously, did you see <a href="http://twitter.com/anildash/status/275055322102636544" title="High Five Fist Bump" target="_blank">this tweet</a>?)</li>
</ol>


<p>Looking forward to seeing how this goes :)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby Heroes, Open Source, and Hacking to Prevent Human Trafficking]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/ruby-heroes-open-source-and-hacking-to-prevent-trafficking"/>
    <updated>2012-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/ruby-heroes-open-source-and-hacking-to-prevent-human-trafficking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First and foremost, Congratulations to&nbsp;<a href="http://twitter.com/yokolet">Yoko Harada</a>, one of this year's&nbsp;<a href="http://rubyheroes.com/">Ruby Heroes</a>! She's made substantial contributions to the Ruby community, specifically for her work on open source projects&nbsp;<a href="http://jruby.org/">JRuby</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="http://nokogiri.org">Nokogiri</a>. Yoko inspired me to share an example of one of many projects that were possible thanks to free and open source software, and specifically Nokogiri.<p />In July 2011, Girl Develop It hosted a Hackathon for Humanity (in the Hamptons thanks to&nbsp;<a href="http://twitter.com/dbdj1007">Deborah Jackson</a>&nbsp;&amp;&nbsp;<a href="http://jumpthru.net/">JumpThru</a>!),&nbsp;<a href="http://twitter.com/nahurst">Nathan Hurst</a>&nbsp;and I used Nokogiri to parse data from&nbsp;<a href="http://backpage.com/">Backpage.com</a>&nbsp;and flag potential evidence of human trafficking. We used <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/wget/">wget</a> to pull the posts and Nokogiri to parse the data into a&nbsp;<a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a>&nbsp;application and&nbsp;<a href="http://postgresql.org/">Postgres</a>&nbsp;database, which I then queried to identify potential child prostitution advertisements. We were able to flag hundreds to be investigated and removed by&nbsp;<a href="http://backpage.com/">Backpage.com</a>.<p />The project readme file expands a bit on our methodology- basically, we'd read that many human trafficking rings tend to diversify their crime businesses by engaging in many types of trafficking and other illegal activity, so we cross-referenced some of the phone numbers across different subject areas on the site. We found dozens of posts that once examined by the human eye were clearly not legal, and hardly any false positives. This method proved quite accurate and a lot more manageable than manually sorting through all of the posts.<p />We definitely wouldn't have pulled that off, especially not in a weekend hackathon, without Nokogiri being free, open source, and delightfully easy to use.<p />The project is on Github at&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/girldevelopit/traffic-report">https://github.com/girldevelopit/traffic-report</a>. Note that this is the code from a one-time weekend project, but if you're interested in forking or just learning from it and building a service to continue this work, please do! We're happy to share any undocumented lessons or answer questions, just reach out by email (<a href="mailto:nathan@ohours.org">nathan@ohours.org</a> or <a href="mailto:vanessa@developersforgood.org">vanessa@developersforgood.org</a>).<p /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PG East 2011 & Defense Against the Dark Arts]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/pg-east-2011-defense-against-the-dark-arts"/>
    <updated>2011-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/pg-east-2011-defense-against-the-dark-arts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, March 22-25, the PostgreSQL community (with guest appearances by MongoDB advocates &amp; users) came to NYC for PG East 2011. At the beginning of the week I wasn't sure how to manage&nbsp;my jealousy of those headed to <a href="http://event.gigaom.com/bigdata/" title="Structure Big Data 2011" target="_blank">GigaOm's Structure Big Data</a>&nbsp;(which, by the way, is at the same time and 5x more expensive), but I didn't think twice about it while meeting and learning from members of the PG community. The days were a mix of talks and sharing war stories in the hallways, and the evenings included happy hours with the <a href="http://meetup.com/postgresql-3" title="NYC PostgreSQL Users Group" target="_blank">NY Postgres Users Group</a>&nbsp;(if you're in NYC, join!) and&nbsp;<a href="http://paperlesspost.com" title="Paperless Post" target="_blank">Paperless Post</a>.</p>


<p>I gave a talk that briefly addresses what an ORM (Object-Relational Mapper) is and how they are great for application development, but can be a headache for DBAs. Most of the talk focuses on key factors to consider in evaluating an ORM and in maintaining and scaling systems that use ORMs. The intended audience for the talk is:</p>


<ul>
<li>DBAs curious if ORMs might actually be the devil</li>
<li>Startups or development shops without a data expert on hand</li>
<li>Lone DBAs or small DBA teams that are seriously outnumbered by developers using ORMs</li>
<li>Developers who want to understand more about ensuring applications create usable data</li>
<li>Developers using ORMs who think the database might be a performance bottleneck</li>
</ul>


<p>Obviously the slides are never quite the same as a live talk, but I tried to make them somewhat independently valuable:</p>


<div style=""><strong style="display: block; margin: 12px 0 4px;"><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/DBNess/defense-against-the-dark-arts-protecting-your-data-from-orms" title="Defense Against the Dark Arts: Protecting Your Data from ORMs">Defense Against the Dark Arts: Protecting Your Data from ORMs</a></strong> 
<object height="355" width="425">
<param name="movie" value="http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=defenseagainstthedarkarts-110323005018-phpapp01&amp;stripped_title=defense-against-the-dark-arts-protecting-your-data-from-orms&amp;userName=DBNess" />
<param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" />
<param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always" /> <embed src="http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=defenseagainstthedarkarts-110323005018-phpapp01&amp;stripped_title=defense-against-the-dark-arts-protecting-your-data-from-orms&amp;userName=DBNess" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" height="355" width="425"></embed>
</object>
<div style="padding: 5px 0 12px;">View more <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/">presentations</a> from <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/DBNess">Vanessa Hurst</a></div>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TEDx 636 Eleventh Ave NYC]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/tedx-636-eleventh-ave-nyc-coding-for-humanity"/>
    <updated>2011-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/tedx-636-eleventh-ave-nyc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On December 7, 2010 I had the honor of speaking at a local TEDx event, TEDx 636 Eleventh Ave, organized around the TED Women conference in DC. I spoke briefly about my path to becoming a computer programmer. I wish I'd known earlier what incredible potential for impact careers in technology hold. I hope more women and men, young and old, throw away preconceptions and approach programming as a way of impacting humanity.</p>


<p><object height="300" width="500"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/FBayVlnaBw0?fs=1&amp;hl=en_US" /></param><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /></param><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always" /></param><embed allowfullscreen="true" src="http://www.youtube.com/v/FBayVlnaBw0?fs=1&amp;hl=en_US" allowscriptaccess="always" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" height="300" width="500"></embed></object></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Women in Tech: The Opportunity]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity"/>
    <updated>2010-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><span style=""> </span>In the United States, STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) fields are hurting. You know you've got a problem when even the government is trying to solve it (as shown by the White House's&nbsp;<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/issues/education/educate-innovate" target="_blank">Educate to Innovate</a>&nbsp;initiative&nbsp;(<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/president-obama-launches-educate-innovate-campaign-excellence-science-technology-en" target="_blank">Nov. 2009</a>)&nbsp;and private-sector CEO engagement in&nbsp;<a href="http://www.changetheequation.org/" target="_blank">Change The Equation</a>&nbsp;(<a href="http://news.thomasnet.com/IMT/archives/2010/09/inside-change-the-equation-stem-education-initiative.html" target="_blank">Sept. 2010</a>)). Raw data clearly shows that the US awards a significantly smaller portion of science and engineering bachelor's degrees than the majority of reporting countries (<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_414.asp" target="_blank">NCES</a>). Within that already meek representation, computer science stands out as a dearth among dearths.</div>


<p />
<div>So techies are awesome, but we aren't training nearly enough of them. Where could we possibly find more potential programmers??</div>
<p />
<div>The New York Times offers a classic&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/imagepages/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.html" target="_blank">visualization of the CS gender gap</a>:</div>
<br />
<div><img src="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.gif"></div>
<div>This visualization shows data through 2004. It has only gotten worse since then.&nbsp;In the US in 2008,&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_268.asp" target="_blank">57%</a>&nbsp;of all&nbsp;bachelor's degree recipients were female, but only&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_303.asp" target="_blank">17%</a>&nbsp;of bachelor's degrees in computer and information sciences were awarded to women.&nbsp;Oops. Looks like we found our missing programmers!</div>
<p />
<div>There are certainly plenty of underrepresented groups in computer science, but the male/female gap is by far the most severe and spans a variety of racial and socioeconomic groups, so it makes sense to address as a distinct priority.</div>
<p />
<div>As recent as a few weeks ago, a dedicated&nbsp;<a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/09/28/girls-in-blech/" target="_blank">Women In Tech panel at TechCrunch Disrupt</a>&nbsp;established that everyone knows women are underrepresented in tech (especially tech startups), but left viewers wanting when it came to solutions. A few panel members noted that what we could really use is more women studying computer science or learning to program. I wholeheartedly agree.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
