<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: computer programming | Code for Humanity]]></title>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/blog/categories/computer-programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-25T13:05:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vanessahurst.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vanessa Hurst]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code.org: What most schools don't teach]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/blog/2013/02/28/code-org-what-most-schools-don-t-teach/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/blog/2013/02/28/code-org-what-most-schools-don-t-teach</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="posterous_short_quote">
<p>The programmers of tomorrow are the wizards of the future. You're going to look like you have magic powers...</p>
</blockquote>


<p><cite>- Gabe Newell, Founder of Valve</cite></p>


<p><a href="http://code.org" title="Code.org">Code.org</a>&nbsp;just launched with the vision that <strong>every student in every school should have the opportunity to learn how to code</strong>&nbsp;as well as a film encouraging every student to do so.</p>


<p>I'm grateful to have contributed to this inspiring short film by Lesley Chilcott, producer of <em><span style="font-family: arial, sans-serif;">Waiting for Superman</span></em>, alongside Mark Zuckerberg, Bill Gates, <a href="http://bronwengrimes.com/" title="Bronwen Grimes" target="_blank">Bronwen Grimes</a>, Chris Bosh, Will.I.Am, <a href="http://silenok.com" title="Elena Silenok" target="_blank">Elena Silenok</a>, Jack Dorsey, Drew Houston, Ruchi Sanghvi, and other oustanding people.</p>


<p>If you're a teacher, know a teacher, sit next to a teacher on the subway, or otherwise have means to spread the word, please do so! No one is too old or too... anything, really, to learn how to code.&nbsp;There are several lengths and versions of <a href="http://www.code.org/teach" title="Code.org Teaching Videos" target="_blank">the film available</a>, and you can start <a href="http://code.org/learn" title="Learn to Code" target="_blank">learning to code</a> right away.</p>


<p>Once you're ready, we'll be thrilled to have you improve the world by contributing to social good coding projects at&nbsp;<a href="http://codemontage.com" title="CodeMontage: Improve your skills while improving the world" target="_blank">CodeMontage</a>.</p>


<p><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/nKIu9yen5nc" frameborder="0" height="315" width="560"></iframe></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Women in Tech: The Opportunity]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity"/>
    <updated>2010-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><span style=""> </span>In the United States, STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) fields are hurting. You know you've got a problem when even the government is trying to solve it (as shown by the White House's&nbsp;<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/issues/education/educate-innovate" target="_blank">Educate to Innovate</a>&nbsp;initiative&nbsp;(<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/president-obama-launches-educate-innovate-campaign-excellence-science-technology-en" target="_blank">Nov. 2009</a>)&nbsp;and private-sector CEO engagement in&nbsp;<a href="http://www.changetheequation.org/" target="_blank">Change The Equation</a>&nbsp;(<a href="http://news.thomasnet.com/IMT/archives/2010/09/inside-change-the-equation-stem-education-initiative.html" target="_blank">Sept. 2010</a>)). Raw data clearly shows that the US awards a significantly smaller portion of science and engineering bachelor's degrees than the majority of reporting countries (<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_414.asp" target="_blank">NCES</a>). Within that already meek representation, computer science stands out as a dearth among dearths.</div>


<p />
<div>So techies are awesome, but we aren't training nearly enough of them. Where could we possibly find more potential programmers??</div>
<p />
<div>The New York Times offers a classic&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/imagepages/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.html" target="_blank">visualization of the CS gender gap</a>:</div>
<br />
<div><img src="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.gif"></div>
<div>This visualization shows data through 2004. It has only gotten worse since then.&nbsp;In the US in 2008,&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_268.asp" target="_blank">57%</a>&nbsp;of all&nbsp;bachelor's degree recipients were female, but only&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_303.asp" target="_blank">17%</a>&nbsp;of bachelor's degrees in computer and information sciences were awarded to women.&nbsp;Oops. Looks like we found our missing programmers!</div>
<p />
<div>There are certainly plenty of underrepresented groups in computer science, but the male/female gap is by far the most severe and spans a variety of racial and socioeconomic groups, so it makes sense to address as a distinct priority.</div>
<p />
<div>As recent as a few weeks ago, a dedicated&nbsp;<a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/09/28/girls-in-blech/" target="_blank">Women In Tech panel at TechCrunch Disrupt</a>&nbsp;established that everyone knows women are underrepresented in tech (especially tech startups), but left viewers wanting when it came to solutions. A few panel members noted that what we could really use is more women studying computer science or learning to program. I wholeheartedly agree.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
