<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: startups | Code for Humanity]]></title>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/blog/categories/startups/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-25T13:05:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vanessahurst.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vanessa Hurst]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scouting for Open Source Software with WebFWD]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/scouting-for-open-source-software-with-webfwd"/>
    <updated>2012-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/scouting-for-open-source-software-with-webfwd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dearest Open Source Software,</p>


<p>I know you've always been a bit worried about the future - no need to worry, you've got friends. Friends who love you and want you to be successful and sustainable. Among those friends are the crew at Mozilla's Open Innovation Group - and this time they've put together something really exciting: the <a href="http://webfwd.org">WebFWD</a> accelerator.</p>


<p><strong>WebFWD is an accelerator for businesses based on open innovation</strong>. The program is entirely remote and lasts 12 weeks with eight of intense education and four of focused product development. At the end of the program, companies may be eligible for <a href="https://webfwd.org/about/fund/">funding from Mozilla</a>.</p>


<p>Curious what kinds of products and companies WebFWD crew has been working on so far? Here are the&nbsp;current WebFWD Teams:</p>


<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><a href="http://codebender.cc/">Codebender</a>, aka hardware hacking made easy, <a href="http://twitter.com/codebender_cc">@codebender_cc</a><br /> <a href="http://harp.io/">Harp</a>, easy website deployment using Dropbox, <a href="http://twitter.com/harpplatform">@HarpPlatform</a><br /><a href="http://linklib.org/">Linklib</a>, open source video commentary library<br /> <a href="http://openjumpstarts.org/">Open Jumpstarts</a>, try a full web app with just one click, <a href="http://twitter.com/openjumpstarts">@OpenJumpstarts</a><br /><a href="http://sketchfab.com/">Sketchfab</a>, interactive 3D content publishing, <a href="http://twitter.com/sketchfab">@Sketchfab</a><br /> <a href="http://www.triv.io/">Trivio</a>, streamlined data wrangling<br /><a href="http://beta.wercker.com/">Wercker</a>, simplified continuous deployment, <a href="http://twitter.com/wercker">@wercker</a><p /></p>
<p>And a few of my favorites from the many awesome WebFWD Alumni:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><a href="http://cashmusic.org/">CASHmusic</a>, Wordpress::Bloggers::CASHMusic::Musicians, <a href="http://twitter.com/cashmusic">@cashmusic</a><br /><a href="http://www.tomahawk-player.org/">Tomahawk</a>, a delightful open source iTunes replacement, <a href="http://twitter.com/tomahawk">@tomahawk</a><br /> <a href="http://www.propelly.com/">Propelly</a>, super simple sales of digital files, <a href="http://twitter.com/propelly">@propelly</a></p>
<p>
<p>Ready to turn your open source labor love into your main gig?&nbsp;<a href="http://webfwd.org/apply">Apply to WebFWD</a>!</p>
</p>
<p>If you have any questions about WebFWD (<a href="http://twitter.com/MozWebFWD">@MozWebFWD</a>), please feel free to <a href="mailto:vanessa@developersforgood.org">email me</a>&nbsp;or sign up for a conversation via <a href="http://ohours.org/dbness">Ohours</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Piercing the Tech Networking Bubble with Open Mentoring]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/open-mentoring"/>
    <updated>2011-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/piercing-the-tech-networking-bubble-with-open-mentoring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night I watched&nbsp;Soledad O'Brien's CNN <a href="http://inamerica.blogs.cnn.com/category/black-in-america/" target="_blank">Black in America: The New Promised Land - Silicon Valley</a> special that offered a lesser known perspective on an industry I know well. The special followed black entrepreneurs who participated in the first annual <a href="http://www.newmeaccelerator.com/" target="_blank">NewMe startup accelerator</a>. After the special aired, I watched <a href="http://www.marioarmstrong.com/on-air/innovation-nation-the-official-live-webcast/">Mario Armstrong's Town Hall</a> and heard plenty of great advice from accomplished panelists of different races and backgrounds. In just an hour and a half they covered a range of cultural problems and shared opinions on solutions.</p>


<p>The best thing about pieces like this is that they focus on a problem and hopefully, get us all riled up to fix it - but do we? One of the audience members stood up and reminded the room that the change wasn't going to come down from the panelists, but come up from them - that they had to make the change for themselves.</p>


<p>Right here and right now, I'd like to do something to address this problem. We heard over and over again the importance of networks and of having the right conversation with the right people. Entrepreneurs were advised to "insert" themselves into social circles of Silicon Valley. I agree with panelist/engineer/founder <a href="http://twitter.com/hankwilliams">Hank Williams</a> that taking baby steps is the key to both programming and life, so here's my step for today:</p>


<p><strong>I'll be hosting open video chats specifically to mentor people who aren't already in my established social circles.</strong></p>


<p>Here's&nbsp;<a href="http://ohours.org/DBNess" title="My Open Mentoring Availability" target="_blank">My Open Mentoring Availability</a>, starting with</p>


<ul>
<li><a href="http://ohours.org/officehours/3128">Thursday, November 17</a> at 1:00pm, 1:15pm, and 1:30pm ET&nbsp;</li>
<li><a href="http://ohours.org/officehours/3130">Wednesday, November 23</a> at 2:00pm, 2:15pm, and 2:30pm ET</li>
</ul>


<p>My goal is to make it less uncomfortable for new people to get involved in tech and startup communities.</p>


<p>I hope to see other leaders of these communities offer their time and guidance as well. I've written some and talked a whole lot about personal scheduling and efficiency, so I want to be clear that this is a relatively small, effective commitment - I plan to give 45 minutes to conversations with up to three new people and to spend the remaining 15 minutes of my alotted hour following up or laying the groundwork to help those people. This will amount to roughly one hour a week. If you'd like to help, too,&nbsp;consider&nbsp;<a href="http://ohours.org/topics/mentoring">joining the Ohours mentoring topic</a>.</p>


<p>If you or anyone you know aspires to be an entrepreneur, engineer,&nbsp;teacher,&nbsp;computer scientist, wielder of data, or perhaps is now a girl scout, military brat, data lover, amateur organizational psychologist, blonde - or maybe none of the above, but would like to talk with someone who is - please send them my way. My door is <a href="http://ohours.org/DBNess">wide open</a>.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
