<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: computer science | Code for Humanity]]></title>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/blog/categories/computer-science/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-03T23:13:02-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://vanessahurst.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vanessa Hurst]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code.org: What most schools don't teach]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/blog/2013/02/28/code-org-what-most-schools-don-t-teach/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/blog/2013/02/28/code-org-what-most-schools-don-t-teach</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="posterous_short_quote">
<p>The programmers of tomorrow are the wizards of the future. You're going to look like you have magic powers...</p>
</blockquote>


<p><cite>- Gabe Newell, Founder of Valve</cite></p>


<p><a href="http://code.org" title="Code.org">Code.org</a>&nbsp;just launched with the vision that <strong>every student in every school should have the opportunity to learn how to code</strong>&nbsp;as well as a film encouraging every student to do so.</p>


<p>I'm grateful to have contributed to this inspiring short film by Lesley Chilcott, producer of <em><span style="font-family: arial, sans-serif;">Waiting for Superman</span></em>, alongside Mark Zuckerberg, Bill Gates, <a href="http://bronwengrimes.com/" title="Bronwen Grimes" target="_blank">Bronwen Grimes</a>, Chris Bosh, Will.I.Am, <a href="http://silenok.com" title="Elena Silenok" target="_blank">Elena Silenok</a>, Jack Dorsey, Drew Houston, Ruchi Sanghvi, and other oustanding people.</p>


<p>If you're a teacher, know a teacher, sit next to a teacher on the subway, or otherwise have means to spread the word, please do so! No one is too old or too... anything, really, to learn how to code.&nbsp;There are several lengths and versions of <a href="http://www.code.org/teach" title="Code.org Teaching Videos" target="_blank">the film available</a>, and you can start <a href="http://code.org/learn" title="Learn to Code" target="_blank">learning to code</a> right away.</p>


<p>Once you're ready, we'll be thrilled to have you improve the world by contributing to social good coding projects at&nbsp;<a href="http://codemontage.com" title="CodeMontage: Improve your skills while improving the world" target="_blank">CodeMontage</a>.</p>


<p><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/nKIu9yen5nc" frameborder="0" height="315" width="560"></iframe></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Women in Tech: The Opportunity]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity"/>
    <updated>2010-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><span style=""> </span>In the United States, STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) fields are hurting. You know you've got a problem when even the government is trying to solve it (as shown by the White House's&nbsp;<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/issues/education/educate-innovate" target="_blank">Educate to Innovate</a>&nbsp;initiative&nbsp;(<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/president-obama-launches-educate-innovate-campaign-excellence-science-technology-en" target="_blank">Nov. 2009</a>)&nbsp;and private-sector CEO engagement in&nbsp;<a href="http://www.changetheequation.org/" target="_blank">Change The Equation</a>&nbsp;(<a href="http://news.thomasnet.com/IMT/archives/2010/09/inside-change-the-equation-stem-education-initiative.html" target="_blank">Sept. 2010</a>)). Raw data clearly shows that the US awards a significantly smaller portion of science and engineering bachelor's degrees than the majority of reporting countries (<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_414.asp" target="_blank">NCES</a>). Within that already meek representation, computer science stands out as a dearth among dearths.</div>


<p />
<div>So techies are awesome, but we aren't training nearly enough of them. Where could we possibly find more potential programmers??</div>
<p />
<div>The New York Times offers a classic&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/imagepages/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.html" target="_blank">visualization of the CS gender gap</a>:</div>
<br />
<div><img src="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.gif"></div>
<div>This visualization shows data through 2004. It has only gotten worse since then.&nbsp;In the US in 2008,&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_268.asp" target="_blank">57%</a>&nbsp;of all&nbsp;bachelor's degree recipients were female, but only&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_303.asp" target="_blank">17%</a>&nbsp;of bachelor's degrees in computer and information sciences were awarded to women.&nbsp;Oops. Looks like we found our missing programmers!</div>
<p />
<div>There are certainly plenty of underrepresented groups in computer science, but the male/female gap is by far the most severe and spans a variety of racial and socioeconomic groups, so it makes sense to address as a distinct priority.</div>
<p />
<div>As recent as a few weeks ago, a dedicated&nbsp;<a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/09/28/girls-in-blech/" target="_blank">Women In Tech panel at TechCrunch Disrupt</a>&nbsp;established that everyone knows women are underrepresented in tech (especially tech startups), but left viewers wanting when it came to solutions. A few panel members noted that what we could really use is more women studying computer science or learning to program. I wholeheartedly agree.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Software Developers Rock (and Could Be Even Better)]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/why-software-developers-rock"/>
    <updated>2010-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/why-software-developers-rock-and-could-be-even-better-</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>Software developers are awesome. More specifically:</div>


<p />
<div>Software developers make significant contributions to the community for free - both free as in beer and free as in speech - which lead to <a href="http://creativecommons.org/">Creative Commons</a> and similar licenses which are growing in popularity across industries. Our forums (e.g. <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/faq" target="_blank">Stack Overflow</a>,&nbsp;<a href="http://ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html" target="_blank">Hacker News</a>,&nbsp;and hundreds of technology-specific online user groups) are some of the most meritocratic that exist today - for the most part, positions are attacked instead of individuals. These benefits come from a base of people who genuinely understand logic (and thus can avoid silly ad hominem attacks) and who are visionaries, always sharing ideas and watching out for the next big breakthrough.</div>
<p />
<div>Software developers are exceedingly generous. We do barcamps and hackathons to address global crises ala <a href="http://crisiscommons.org/about-us/" target="_blank">CrisisCamp</a>, we help non-profits en masse through weekend pro-bono <a href="http://givecamp.org/" target="_blank">GiveCamps</a> and through groups like <a href="http://meetup.developersforgood.org" target="_blank">Developers for Good</a>. We're addressing worldwide healthcare needs through transparent, open-source projects like <a href="http://openmrs.org/" target="_blank">OpenMRS</a> and improving local government through projects like <a href="http://civiccommons.com/" target="_blank">CivicCommons</a>&nbsp;and <a href="http://www.codeforamerica.org">Code for America</a>.</div>
<p />
<div>Software developers have built exceptional communities off of good ideas and a lot of hard work, but we've certainly never been fans of the status quo. We're always wondering - <em>how can we get better</em>? Individual software developers improve by picking up new languages, sharing their code through GitHub, or even by creating frameworks like Rails that dramatically improve the efficiency of others. The next step in that evolution is asking as a community, <em>what can we do to collectively improve</em>? Sure, we can say that since we're already productive it's okay to just keep on keeping on, but that doesn't seem true to our potential as individuals or as a community. It's also boring. Let's get more awesome instead.</div>
<p />
<div>Research shows that&nbsp;<a href="http://www.asanet.org/images/journals/docs/pdf/asr/Apr09ASRFeature.pdf">diversity is good business</a>&nbsp;[PDF]&nbsp;and <a href="http://ascc.artsci.wustl.edu/%7Eksawyer/groupgenius/excerpt.html" target="_blank">collaboration is the key to breakthrough creativity</a>, so&nbsp;<em><span style="font-size: medium;">the next great evolution of the software community is to increase diversity.&nbsp;</span></em>The true nature of our field is to seek optimization, to continually refine and improve. Broadening the range of perspectives involved in our work will fuel our ability to innovate as well as propel our economy. It will also increase the awesome.</div>
<p />
<div>
<div>It's rational, if not empathetic, to hear the buzzword "diversity" and think - why does it matter if the ratio in programming doesn't represent the greater population? Why more diverse, rather than just more?&nbsp;Software developers are rapidly becoming the gatekeepers for global knowledge-sharing and connectivity. Computers permeate our lives - shouldn't the community of people who control them be as innovative and yes, as representative, as possible?</div>
<p />
<div><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frances_E._Allen">Fran Allen</a>,&nbsp;the first female recipient of the Turing award, summed it up quite well in an interview with Peter Seibel for&nbsp;<a href="http://www.codersatwork.com/">Coders At Work</a>,</div>
<p />
<blockquote>
<div><em>It's such a transformative field for society as a whole. And without the involvement of a diverse group of people, the results of what we do are not going to be appealing or useful to all aspects of our society. A piece of our challenge is to make computing, and all that it enables, accessible to everyone. That's an ideal.</em></div>
</blockquote>
<p>So, my beloved software developers - the state of our industry isn't about yelling or blaming or terse 140 character twitfits - we are way too awesome for that. What we do have, though, is <a href="http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity">a clear opportunity to improve</a>. In order to grow and improve as an industry, we need to engage more diverse minds in software development.</p>
<p>A few ways to capitalize on this immense opportunity, and improve our field:</p>
<ul>
<li>Continue above stated awesomeness by writing great code and using your skills to improve the world</li>
<li>Encourage anyone and everyone you know (and even those you don't know) to get involved in software development</li>
<li>Mentor an aspiring developer on your next side project&nbsp;(perhaps a&nbsp;<a href="http://meetup.girldevelopit.com">Girl Develop It</a>&nbsp;student)</li>
<li>Seek simple ways to make your work more accessible to non-expert users (e.g. add dreaded Documentation)</li>
</ul>
<p>Feel free to share constructive ideas for engaging more minds in software development in the comments or by contacting me directly.</p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
