<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: women in tech | Code for Humanity]]></title>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/blog/categories/women-in-tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-25T12:12:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vanessahurst.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vanessa Hurst]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW 2011 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/sxsw-2011-review"/>
    <updated>2011-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/sxsw-2011-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year at South by Southwest Interactive, I</p>


<p>Ate a five-course local dinner one table from Jake Gyllenhaal at delicious WINK restaurant. Despite the sketchy law offices, bail bonds for sale, dark alleys and many cops on our walk to the restaurant, I have no regrets about being a pedestrian anywhere for as long as possible. And JG is way more attractive in person than the movies (even my husband agrees).</p>


<p>Met Marissa Mayer, talked about iterating a product quickly with analytics. Told her we had similar paths to programming and that I'm grateful she shared her story with the internets. After this my life was complete, so I fully indulged in not attending very many panels the rest of the week.</p>


<p>Met Jane McGonigal, started reading her awesome book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Reality-Broken-Games-Better-Change/dp/1594202850" title="Reality is Broken on Amazon" target="_blank">Reality is Broken</a> complete with Fiero autograph, and thanked her for yet another demonstration of how technology can change the world for the better. The book is changing my life already.</p>


<p>Met the technical and talented team <a href="http://twitter.com/lindaliukas" title="Linda on Twitter" target="_blank">Linda</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/karrisaarinen" title="Karri on Twitter" target="_blank">Karri</a> of <a href="http://railsgirls.com" title="Rails Girls" target="_blank">Rails Girls</a>, who host awesome Ruby on Rails workshops in Finland, commiserated, and hopefully shared some of what we've learned at Girl Develop It.</p>


<p><span style="text-decoration: line-through;">Met </span>Accosted and introduced myself to Jennifer Lim, CEO of Delivering Happiness and original Zappos culture book writer. I forgot to tell her and Tony Hsieh that I reference the hierarchy of happiness on a regular basis and am so, so into them.</p>


<p>Met awesome hackers of all sorts and learned some cool hacks at Hacker Underground, including how to leave commands out of your command line history and how to get even more food in your Chipotle burrito.</p>


<p>Launched a startup of my very own, with Sara Chipps and Pamela Fox: <a href="http://stashyourstache.com">http://stashyourstache.com</a>.</p>


<p>All in all, had an awesome week. Excited to be back in NYC and hoping our weather can compete with Austin sometime soon :).</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Women in Tech: The Opportunity]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity"/>
    <updated>2010-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessahurst.com/women-in-tech-the-opportunity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><span style=""> </span>In the United States, STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) fields are hurting. You know you've got a problem when even the government is trying to solve it (as shown by the White House's&nbsp;<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/issues/education/educate-innovate" target="_blank">Educate to Innovate</a>&nbsp;initiative&nbsp;(<a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/president-obama-launches-educate-innovate-campaign-excellence-science-technology-en" target="_blank">Nov. 2009</a>)&nbsp;and private-sector CEO engagement in&nbsp;<a href="http://www.changetheequation.org/" target="_blank">Change The Equation</a>&nbsp;(<a href="http://news.thomasnet.com/IMT/archives/2010/09/inside-change-the-equation-stem-education-initiative.html" target="_blank">Sept. 2010</a>)). Raw data clearly shows that the US awards a significantly smaller portion of science and engineering bachelor's degrees than the majority of reporting countries (<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_414.asp" target="_blank">NCES</a>). Within that already meek representation, computer science stands out as a dearth among dearths.</div>


<p />
<div>So techies are awesome, but we aren't training nearly enough of them. Where could we possibly find more potential programmers??</div>
<p />
<div>The New York Times offers a classic&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/imagepages/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.html" target="_blank">visualization of the CS gender gap</a>:</div>
<br />
<div><img src="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2007/04/17/science/20070417_COMP_GRAPHIC.gif"></div>
<div>This visualization shows data through 2004. It has only gotten worse since then.&nbsp;In the US in 2008,&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_268.asp" target="_blank">57%</a>&nbsp;of all&nbsp;bachelor's degree recipients were female, but only&nbsp;<a href="http://nces.ed.gov/programs/digest/d09/tables/dt09_303.asp" target="_blank">17%</a>&nbsp;of bachelor's degrees in computer and information sciences were awarded to women.&nbsp;Oops. Looks like we found our missing programmers!</div>
<p />
<div>There are certainly plenty of underrepresented groups in computer science, but the male/female gap is by far the most severe and spans a variety of racial and socioeconomic groups, so it makes sense to address as a distinct priority.</div>
<p />
<div>As recent as a few weeks ago, a dedicated&nbsp;<a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/09/28/girls-in-blech/" target="_blank">Women In Tech panel at TechCrunch Disrupt</a>&nbsp;established that everyone knows women are underrepresented in tech (especially tech startups), but left viewers wanting when it came to solutions. A few panel members noted that what we could really use is more women studying computer science or learning to program. I wholeheartedly agree.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
